So, this book that I have in my hand
هذا الكتاب الذي بين يدي
is a directory of everybody who had an email address
عبارة عن دليل عن كل شخص لديه بريد إلكتروني
in 1982. (Laughter)
في 1982. [ضحك]
Actually, it's deceptively large.
في الواقع، سماكته مضللة .
There's actually only about 20 people on each page,
في الواقع لايوجد سوى 20 شخص في كل صفحة,
because we have the name, address
لأن لدينا الإسم والعنوان,
and telephone number of every single person.
ورقم الهاتف لكل شخص.
And, in fact, everybody's listed twice,
في الواقع, كل شخص قد أُدرج مرتين,
because it's sorted once by name and once by email address.
مرّة بالإسم ومرّة بالبريد الإلكتروني.
Obviously a very small community.
من الواضح أنه مجتمع صغير جدًا.
There were only two other Dannys on the Internet then.
كان هناك اثنين غيري على الإنترنت فقط.
I knew them both.
وأعرف كلاهما.
We didn't all know each other,
لم نكن نعرف بعضنا البعض،
but we all kind of trusted each other,
ولكن كنّا نثق ببعضنا البعض,
and that basic feeling of trust
وهذا الشعور الأساسي بالثقة
permeated the whole network,
انتشر عبر الشبكة,
and there was a real sense that
وكان هناك شعور حقيقي أن
we could depend on each other to do things.
بإمكاننا أن نعتمد على بعضنا البعض في فعل الأشياء.
So just to give you an idea of the level of trust in this community,
فقط لإعطائكم فكرة عن مستوى الثقة في هذا المجتمع،
let me tell you what it was like
دعوني أخبركم ما كان عليه
to register a domain name in the early days.
تسجيل اسم النطاق في الأيام الأولى.
Now, it just so happened that I got to register
تبين لي أنني سجّلت
the third domain name on the Internet.
إسم النطاق الثالث على الإنترنت.
So I could have anything I wanted
لذا كان بإمكاني اختيار أي شيء أريده
other than bbn.com and symbolics.com.
بخلاف bbn.com و symbolics.com
So I picked think.com, but then I thought,
لذا اخترت think.com , ولكن بعد ذلك فكّرت,
you know, there's a lot of really interesting names out there.
تعلمون, هناك الكثير من الاسماء المثيرة للاهتمام.
Maybe I should register a few extras just in case.
ربما يجب عليّ تسجيل بعض منها للاحتياط.
And then I thought, "Nah, that wouldn't be very nice."
ثم قلت في نفسي "لا، هذا لن يكون لطيفًا جدا."
(Laughter)
[ضحك]
That attitude of only taking what you need
ذلك النهج الذي تأخذ فيه ماتحتاج فقط
was really what everybody had on the network in those days,
كان لدى كل شخص على الشبكة في تلك الأيام,
and in fact, it wasn't just the people on the network,
وفي الواقع, لم تكن مجرد أشخاص على الشبكة,
but it was actually kind of built into the protocols
ولكنه كان في الواقع نوع من صلب بروتوكولات
of the Internet itself.
الإنترنت نفسها.
So the basic idea of I.P., or Internet protocol,
لذا الفكرة الأساسية للـ آي بي, أو بروتوكول الإنترنت,
and the way that the -- the routing algorithm that used it,
والطريقة التي تستخدم في توجيه الخوارزميات,
were fundamentally "from each according to their ability,
كانت في الأساس، "من كلٍّ حسب قدرته،
to each according to their need."
وإلى كلٍّ حسب حاجته".
And so, if you had some extra bandwidth,
وإذا كان لديك عرض نطاق(معدّل نقل بيانات)اضافي,
you'd deliver a message for someone.
بإمكانك إيصال رسالة لشخص ما.
If they had some extra bandwidth, they would deliver a message for you.
وإذا كان لديهم عرض نطاق(معدّل نقل بيانات)إضافي, يمكنهم إيصال رسالة لك.
You'd kind of depend on people to do that,
ستكون نوعًا ما معتمدًا على الناس لفعل ذلك,
and that was the building block.
كانت تلك اللبنة الأولى.
It was actually interesting that such a communist principle
كان لافتا أن مثل هذا المبدأ الشيوعي
was the basis of a system developed during the Cold War
كان الأساس لنظام تم تطويره خلال الحرب الباردة
by the Defense Department,
من قبل وزارة الدفاع,
but it obviously worked really well,
ولكن من الواضح انها عملت بشكل جيد،
and we all saw what happened with the Internet.
وكلّنا رأينا ما حدث مع الإنترنت.
It was incredibly successful.
كان نجاحًا باهرًا.
In fact, it was so successful that there's no way
في الواقع، كان نجاحًا لدرجة أنه لا توجد وسيلة
that these days you could make a book like this.
هذه الأيام لعمل كتاب مثل هذا.
My rough calculation is it would be about 25 miles thick.
حساباتي التقريبية تقول أن سماكته ستكون حوالي 25 ميلاً.
But, of course, you couldn't do it,
لكن بالطبع, لن تستطيعوا القيام بذلك,
because we don't know the names of all the people
لإننا لانعلم أسماء كل الناس
with Internet or email addresses,
في الإنترنت أو الذين لديهم بريد إلكتروني,
and even if we did know their names,
وحتى لو علمنا بأسمائهم,
I'm pretty sure that they would not want their name,
أنا متأكد أنهم لن يقبلوا لإسمائهم,
address and telephone number published to everyone.
وعناوينهم وأرقام هواتفهم أن تنشر لأي شخص.
So the fact is that there's a lot of bad guys on the Internet these days,
في الواقع هناك الكثير من الأشرار على الإنترنت هذه الأيام،
and so we dealt with that by making
وتعاملنا مع ذلك بإنشاء
walled communities,
المجتمعات المحصّنة,
secure subnetworks, VPNs,
الشبكات الفرعية الآمنة، الشبكات الخاصة الإفتراضية،
little things that aren't really the Internet
بعض الأشياء التي ليست لها علاقة بالإنترنت
but are made out of the same building blocks,
ولكن مصنوعة من لبنات البناء نفسها،
but we're still basically building it out of those
ولكن لا نزال أساسًا نبنيها من منطلق
same building blocks with those same assumptions of trust.
نفس اللبنات مع نفس افتراضات الثقة.
And that means that it's vulnerable
وهذا يعني أنها عرضة
to certain kinds of mistakes that can happen,
لأنواع معينة من الأخطاء التي يمكن أن تحدث،
or certain kinds of deliberate attacks,
أو أنواع معينة من الهجمات المتعمّدة،
but even the mistakes can be bad.
ولكن ستكون أخطاء سيئة للغاية.
So, for instance,
لذلك، على سبيل المثال،
in all of Asia recently,
في كل آسيا مؤخرًا,
it was impossible to get YouTube for a little while
كان من المستحيل الدخول على اليوتيوب لبعض الوقت
because Pakistan made some mistakes
لأن باكستان ارتكبت بعض الأخطاء
in how it was censoring YouTube in its internal network.
في كيفية فرض الرقابة على اليوتيوب في شبكتها الداخلية.
They didn't intend to screw up Asia, but they did
لم تكن تنوي إفساد الأمور في آسيا, ولكنها فعلت
because of the way that the protocols work.
بسبب آلية عمل البروتوكولات.
Another example that may have affected many of you in this audience is,
مثال آخر, من الممكن أن الكثير منكم في هذا الجمهور قد تأثر به,
you may remember a couple of years ago,
ربما تتذكرون قبل بضع سنوات,
all the planes west of the Mississippi were grounded
جميع الطائرات غرب المسيسيبي منعت من الطيران
because a single routing card in Salt Lake City
بسبب بطاقة توجيه في مدينة سولت ليك سيتي
had a bug in it.
كانت فيها علّة.
Now, you don't really think
ألا تعتقدون حقًا أن
that our airplane system depends on the Internet,
نظامنا للطائرات يعتمد على الإنترنت,
and in some sense it doesn't.
ومن ناحية أخرى ليس كذلك.
I'll come back to that later.
سأعود إلى ذلك لاحقًا.
But the fact is that people couldn't take off
لكن في الواقع أن الناس لم يتمكنوا من الاقلاع
because something was going wrong on the Internet,
لأن شيئا ما كان يسير بشكل خاطئ على الإنترنت،
and the router card was down.
وكرت التوجيه كان متعطّلاً.
And so, there are many of those things that start to happen.
وهكذا،هناك الكثير من هذه الأمور التي بدأت تحدث.
Now, there was an interesting thing that happened last April.
هناك أمر مثير للاهتمام حدث في أبريل الماضي.
All of a sudden,
بشكل مفاجئ,
a very large percentage of the traffic on the whole Internet,
نسبة كبيرة جدا من حركة المرور على الإنترنت بأكملها،
including a lot of the traffic between U.S. military installations,
بما في ذلك الكثير من حركة المرور بين المنشآت العسكرية الأمريكية،
started getting re-routed through China.
بدأت بإعادة التوجيه عبر الصين.
So for a few hours, it all passed through China.
ولبضع ساعات مرّت كلها عبر الصين.
Now, China Telecom says it was just an honest mistake,
الاتصالات الصينية قالت إنه خطأ غير مقصود,
and it is actually possible that it was, the way things work,
في الواقع من المحتمل أنه كان كذلك, هكذا تسير الامور,
but certainly somebody could make
لكن من المؤكد أن بإمكان شخص ما افتعال
a dishonest mistake of that sort if they wanted to,
خطأ مقصود من هذا النوع إذا أراد ذلك,
and it shows you how vulnerable the system is even to mistakes.
وهذا يُظهر لكم مدى ضعف هذا النظام حتى مع الأخطاء.
Imagine how vulnerable the system is to deliberate attacks.
تخيلوا مدى هشاشة النظام مع الهجمات المتعمدة.
So if somebody really wanted to attack the United States
لذلك إذا أراد أحدهم مهاجمة الولايات المتحدة
or Western civilization these days,
أو الحضارة الغربية هذه الأيام،
they're not going to do it with tanks.
لن يقوم بذلك باستخدام الدبابات.
That will not succeed.
ذلك لن ينجح.
What they'll probably do is something
ما سيقوم به شيئاً ما
very much like the attack that happened
مثل ماحدث بالضبط في الهجوم
on the Iranian nuclear facility.
على المنشآت النووية الايرانية.
Nobody has claimed credit for that.
ولم تعلن أي جهة مسؤليتها عن ذلك.
There was basically a factory of industrial machines.
كان هناك في الأساس مصنع للآلات الصناعية.
It didn't think of itself as being on the Internet.
لم يفكِّر في نفسه على أنه جزء من الأنترنت.
It thought of itself as being disconnected from the Internet,
اعتقد أنه منفصل من الإنترنت،
but it was possible for somebody to smuggle
ولكن كان من الممكن لشخص ما تهريب
a USB drive in there, or something like that,
محرك أقراص USB هناك، أو شيء من هذا القبيل،
and software got in there that causes the centrifuges,
فوصلت البرمجيات إلى هناك التي أضرت أجهزة الطرد المركزي,
in that case, to actually destroy themselves.
في تلك الحالة, في الواقع قاموا بتدمير أنفسهم.
Now that same kind of software could destroy an oil refinery
مثل هذا النوع من البرمجيات يمكنها تدمير مصفاة لتكرير النفط
or a pharmaceutical factory or a semiconductor plant.
أو مصنعًا للأدوية أو مصانع أشباه الموصلات.
And so there's a lot of -- I'm sure you've read a lot in papers,
انا متأكد أنكم قد قرأتم الكثير في الصحف،
about worries about cyberattacks
حول المخاوف من هجمات قراصنة الكمبيوتر
and defenses against those.
والدفاعات ضد هؤلاء.
But the fact is, people are mostly focused on
لكن في الواقع, ركّز الناس غالبًا على
defending the computers on the Internet,
الدفاع عن أجهزة الكمبيوتر على الإنترنت،
and there's been surprisingly little attention
وكان هناك اهتمام قليل مستغرب
to defending the Internet itself as a communications medium.
للدفاع عن الإنترنت نفسها كوسيلة للاتصال.
And I think we probably do need to pay
أعتقد أننا بحاجة إلى إيلاء اهتمام
some more attention to that, because it's actually kind of fragile.
أكبر في هذا، لأنها في الواقع نوعًا ما هشّة.
So actually, in the early days,
في الأيام الأولى,
back when it was the ARPANET,
عندما كانت ARPANET (شبكة وكالة مشاريع البحوث المتقدمة)
there were actually times -- there was a particular time it failed completely
كان هناك وقت معين انهارت فيه تماما
because one single message processor
بسبب رسالة معالجة واحدة
actually got a bug in it.
تسببت في الخلل.
And the way the Internet works is
والطريقة التي تعمل الإنترنت بها هي
the routers are basically exchanging information
أجهزة التوجيه أساسًا تقوم بمبادلة المعلومات
about how they can get messages to places,
حول كيفية إيصال الرسائل إلى أماكن،
and this one processor, because of a broken card,
وهذه معالجة واحدة، وبسبب البطاقة التالفة،
decided it could actually get a message
تقرر أنها بالفعل بإمكانها إيصال رسالة
to some place in negative time.
إلى مكان ما في الوقت الخطأ.
So, in other words, it claimed it could deliver a message before you sent it.
لذلك، وبعبارة أخرى، ادّعت أن بإمكانها توصيل رسالة قبل أن ترسلها.
So of course, the fastest way to get a message anywhere
وبالطبع، أسرع وسيلة للحصول على رسالة في أي مكان
was to send it to this guy,
كانت بإرسالها إلى هذا الشخص،
who would send it back in time and get it there super early,
الذي بدوره سيقوم بإرسالها في نفس الوقت وإيصالها مبكرًا,
so every message in the Internet
لذا كل رسالة في الإنترنت
started getting switched through this one node,
بدأت بالتحول من خلال هذه العقدة,
and of course that clogged everything up.
وبطبيعة الحال أن انسدّ كل شيء.
Everything started breaking.
كل شيء بدأ ينهار.
The interesting thing was, though,
كان الشيء المثير للاهتمام،
that the sysadmins were able to fix it,
أن مسؤلوا النظام تمكنوا من إصلاحه،
but they had to basically turn every single thing on the Internet off.
لكن كان عليهم إيقاف كل شيء في الإنترنت.
Now, of course you couldn't do that today.
لكن لا يمكننا فعل هذا اليوم.
I mean, everything off, it's like
أعني, إيقاف كل شيئ, سيبدو مثل..
the service call you get from the cable company,
خدمة الاتصال التي حصلتم عليها من شركة الكابلات,
except for the whole world.
باستثناء العالم أجمع.
Now, in fact, they couldn't do it for a lot of reasons today.
في الواقع،لا يمكنهم فعل ذلك اليوم لإسباب كثيرة.
One of the reasons is a lot of their telephones
أحد الأسباب هي كثرة هواتفها
use IP protocol and use things like Skype and so on
تستخدم بروتوكول الإنترنت وتستخدم أشياء مثل سكايبي
that go through the Internet right now,
وما إلى ذلك التي تمر عبر شبكة الإنترنت في الوقت الراهن،
and so in fact we're becoming dependent on it
في الواقع أصبحنا نعتمد عليها
for more and more different things,
لأشياء مختلفة أكثر وأكثر
like when you take off from LAX,
فعندما تقلعون من مطار لوس أنجلس,
you're really not thinking you're using the Internet.
لاتدركون أنكم تستخدمون الإنترنت.
When you pump gas, you really don't think you're using the Internet.
عندما تتزودون بالوقود لاتدركون أنكم تستخدمون الإنترنت.
What's happening increasingly, though, is these systems
مايحدث بشكل متزايد أن هذه الأنظمة
are beginning to use the Internet.
بدأت باستخدام الإنترنت.
Most of them aren't based on the Internet yet,
معظمها لايستند على الإنترنت حتى الآن،
but they're starting to use the Internet for service functions,
ولكنهم بدأوا باستخدام الإنترنت للوظائف الخدمية,
for administrative functions,
للوظائف الإدارية,
and so if you take something like the cell phone system,
فإذا أخذتم شيئاً ما مثل نظام الهاتف النقال,
which is still relatively independent of the Internet for the most part,
الذي لا يزال مستقلاً نسبياً عن الإنترنت في معظمه،
Internet pieces are beginning to sneak into it
أجزاء الإنترنت بدأت بالتسلل إليه
in terms of some of the control and administrative functions,
فيما يتعلق ببعض التحكم و الوظائف الإدارية,
and it's so tempting to use these same building blocks
ومن المغري استخدام نفس لبنات البناء
because they work so well, they're cheap,
لأنها عميلة، ورخيصة،
they're repeated, and so on.
ويتم تكرارها, وما إلى ذلك.
So all of our systems, more and more,
لذلك أنظمتنا، أكثر وأكثر،
are starting to use the same technology
بدأت في استخدام نفس التقنية
and starting to depend on this technology.
وبدأت بالاعتماد على هذه التقنية.
And so even a modern rocket ship these days
حتى سفن الفضاء الحديثة هذه الأيام
actually uses Internet protocol to talk
تستخدم بروتوكول الإنترنت لإجراء المحادثات
from one end of the rocket ship to the other.
من نهاية السفينة إلى الأخرى.
That's crazy. It was never designed to do things like that.
هذا جنون. إنها لم تكن مصصمة لفعل أشياء كهذه.
So we've built this system
لذا بنينا هذا النظام
where we understand all the parts of it,
حينما كنا نفهم كل أجزاءه ,
but we're using it in a very, very different way than we expected to use it,
ولكننا نستخدمه بطريقة مختلفة جدًا عمّا توقعناه له,
and it's gotten a very, very different scale
وأخذ أبعادًا مختلفة جدًا
than it was designed for.
عمّا صمّم له.
And in fact, nobody really exactly understands
وفي الواقع، لا أحد يفهم بالضبط
all the things it's being used for right now.
كل الأشياء التي بدأت تستخدم حاليًّا.
It's turning into one of these big emergent systems
لقد تحول إلى أحد هذه الأنظمة الناشئة الكبرى
like the financial system, where we've designed all the parts
مثل النظام المالي، حيث قمنا بتصميم جميع أجزاءه
but nobody really exactly understands
لكن لا أحد يفهم بالضبط
how it operates and all the little details of it
كيف يعمل وجميع التفاصيل الصغيرة فيه
and what kinds of emergent behaviors it can have.
وما هي أنواع السلوكيات الناشئة التي يمكن أن يحتويها.
And so if you hear an expert talking about the Internet
فإذا سمعت خبير يتحدّث عن الإنترنت
and saying it can do this, or it does do this, or it will do that,
ويقول يمكنها القيام بهذا, أو تقوم بهذا, أو ستقوم بذلك,
you should treat it with the same skepticism
ينبغي أن تتعامل معه مع نفس الشكوك
that you might treat the comments of an economist about the economy
التي تتعامل بها مع تعليقات الخبير الإقتصادي عن الإقتصاد
or a weatherman about the weather, or something like that.
أو الإرصادي حول الطقس، أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
They have an informed opinion,
لديهم رأي مستنير،
but it's changing so quickly that even the experts
لكنه يتغير بسرعة لدرجة أن الخبراء
don't know exactly what's going on.
لا يعلمون ما يجري بالضبط.
So if you see one of these maps of the Internet,
فإذا رأيت أحد خرائط الإنترنت,
it's just somebody's guess.
انها مجرد تخمين شخص ما.
Nobody really knows what the Internet is right now
لا أحد يعرف حقا ماهي الإنترنت هذه اللحضة
because it's different than it was an hour ago.
لأنها مختلفة عمّا كانت عليه قبل ساعة.
It's constantly changing. It's constantly reconfiguring.
انها تتغير باستمرار. ويعاد تشكيلها باستمرار.
And the problem with it is,
والمشكلة معها هي,
I think we are setting ourselves up for a kind of disaster
أننا وضعنا أنفسنا في نوع ما من الكوارث
like the disaster we had in the financial system,
مثل كارثتنا في النظام المالي,
where we take a system that's basically built on trust,
عندما أنشأنا هذا النظام الذي بني أساسًا على الثقة,
was basically built for a smaller-scale system,
كان مبنيًّ في الأساس لنطاق أصغر,
and we've kind of expanded it way beyond the limits
ونوعًا ما وسّعناه خارج الحدود
of how it was meant to operate.
التي كان من المفترض أن يعمل بها.
And so right now, I think it's literally true
حالياًّ، أعتقد أنه صحيح بالمعنى الحرفي
that we don't know what the consequences
أننا لا نعلم ما هي عواقب
of an effective denial-of-service attack
تأثير "هجمات الحرمان من الخدمة"
on the Internet would be,
على الإنترنت سيكون,
and whatever it would be is going to be worse next year,
وأيّاً كان, سيكون العام القادم سيئاً,
and worse next year, and so on.
والعام الذي يليه أكثر سؤاً, وهكذا.
But so what we need is a plan B.
وما نحتاجه هو الخطة B (خطة النسخ الاحتياطي)
There is no plan B right now.
لا توجد حاليًّا خطة B
There's no clear backup system that we've very carefully kept
ليس هناك نظام نسخ احتياطي واضح نبقيه بعناية فائقة
to be independent of the Internet,
منعزلاً عن الإنترنت,
made out of completely different sets of building blocks.
مصنوع من مجموعات مختلفة تمامًا من اللبنات.
So what we need is something that doesn't necessarily
ما نحتاج إليه شيء ليس بالضرورة
have to have the performance of the Internet,
أن نمتلك أداء الإنترنت,
but the police department has to be able
ولكن أن يكون قسم الشرطة قادرا
to call up the fire department even without the Internet,
على استدعاء قسم الإطفاء من دون الإنترنت،
or the hospitals have to order fuel oil.
أو المستشفيات التي تطلب زيت الوقود.
This doesn't need to be a multi-billion-dollar government project.
هذا لا يحتاج إلى أن يكون مشروع حكومي بمليارات الدولارات.
It's actually relatively simple to do, technically,
إنه في الواقع بسيط نسبيًا القيام به من الناحية الفنية,
because it can use existing fibers that are in the ground,
لأنه بالامكان استخدام الألياف الموجودة حاليًّا في الأرض،
existing wireless infrastructure.
و البنية التحتية اللاسلكية القائمة.
It's basically a matter of deciding to do it.
المسألة الأساسية هي اتخاذ القرار لعمل ذلك.
But people won't decide to do it
ولكن الناس لن يقرروا في ذلك
until they recognize the need for it,
حتى يدركوا الحاجة لذلك،
and that's the problem that we have right now.
وهذه هي مشكلتنا في الوقت الحالي.
So there's been plenty of people,
لذلك كان هناك الكثير من الناس،..
plenty of us have been quietly arguing
الكثير منّا كانوا ينادون بهدوء
that we should have this independent system for years,
بأن يكون لدينا هذا النظام المستقل لسنوات،
but it's very hard to get people focused on plan B
لكن من الصعب جدًا أن تركّز انتباه الناس على خطة B
when plan A seems to be working so well.
بينما الخطة A تبدو وكأنها تعمل على ما يرام.
So I think that, if people understand
لذلك أعتقد أنه إذا فهم الناس
how much we're starting to depend on the Internet,
مدى اعتمادنا المتزايد على الإنترنت
and how vulnerable it is,
و مدى ضعفها
we could get focused on
بإمكاننا التركيز على
just wanting this other system to exist,
حاجتنا للنظام الآخر عن الموجود حاليًّا,
and I think if enough people say, "Yeah, I would like to use it,
وإذا كان هناك ما يكفي من الناس يقولون، "نعم، نريد استخدامها،
I'd like to have such a system," then it will get built.
نريد نظامًا كهذا "،سوف يتم بناءه.
It's not that hard a problem.
إنها ليست مشكلة صعبة.
It could definitely be done by people in this room.
يمكن بالتأكيد أن يتم ذلك بواسطة الناس في هذه الغرفة.
And so I think that this is actually,
أعتقد بالفعل,
of all the problems you're going to hear about at the conference,
من كل المشاكل التي ستسمعون عنها في المؤتمر
this is probably one of the very easiest to fix.
هذه على الأرجح واحدة من أسهل المشاكل إصلاحًا.
So I'm happy to get a chance to tell you about it.
لذلك أنا سعيد لحصولي على فرصة لأحدّثكم حول هذا الموضوع.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)